NARRATOR:
Previously on Gotham...
ALFRED: Taking a life will
lead you down a darker path
that you could never imagine.
I know, I've been down it.
I'm not the hero Gotham needs.
ALFRED: Then it's gonna
be a long, bumpy journey back.
You've met Martin, I see.
You and I, we're
more than friends.
We're conspirators.
Oh, no.
You are relieved of
duty, Harvey Bullock.
As of this moment, I am assuming
the captaincy of Gotham Central.
What did you
have to do to get it?
NEWSREADER: Gotham finds itself
in the hands of a ritualistic cop killer
Being called Professor Pyg.
THE PYG: It doesn't stop until
I've butchered every single swine
on Penguin's payroll.
I'm gonna find you.
I hope you do, it's a spectacle.
And you're my
muse, Jimmy Gordon.
My poor lost lambs.
I come to you today with
an offer for this evening.
Fresh biscuits and a
hearty bowl of soup.
I have place settings for six.
Nobody wants some
fresh pumpkin pie?
Smile.
My children.
There are two Gothams.
The haves.
And the have-nots.
I know what it is
to feel like a have-not.
But I say, "Enough."
Here's to giving
the haves a taste
of what it is like to be
a have-not.
Let's begin.
Shall we?
I'll be out of your way
in just a second, Captain.
Harvey.
This isn't how I wanted
things to go down.
And yet, here we are.
You know what I was
thinking about today?
Our first case.
When I told you to walk
Penguin to the end of the pier,
put a bullet in his head
and dump him in the water,
and you wouldn't.
- You thought it was wrong.
- It was.
Well, maybe if you
would have done it,
Falcone would still
be running things
and a lot of people who are
dead would be alive today.
If I could go back,
I'd do the same thing.
'Cause you still don't understand
how the city works, Jim.
You want to be a hero.
And Gotham doesn't need heroes.
It needs people who
will do what is necessary.
You're wrong. If you
show 'em the way,
the people will follow.
I guess we'll just have
to wait and see, huh?
When your leave is up,
there'll be a desk
here waiting for you.
Sit around, watch you all day?
No, thanks.
Right there's
perfect. Thank you.
Beautiful.
I predict this evening's fundraiser
will be a smashing success.
If I want Gotham's
wealthiest families
to support the orphanage,
things have to be perfect.
I appreciate you
taking part, Oswald.
Yes.
- Sadly, a situation has arisen.
- No.
That thing in The Narrows
with your former chief of staff?
No, no. This is
far more serious.
It has to do with Mayor Burke
promoting James Gordon
to captain of the GCPD.
You're not really worried
about James Gordon.
Please.
The issue is the person
who ordered his appointment.
- I see.
- Do you?
Oswald, we both know
the mayor is a weasel.
Someone must've paid him off.
But I don't see why that means
you can't attend my dinner.
Because, my dear,
the mayor has vanished.
But I will find him.
I will learn the
name of my enemy,
and there will be a reckoning.
And that is why I might not
be able to make it this evening.
Very well,
but a few of the
children are doing a song.
Martin is taking part.
It would mean the world
to him if you could come.
Of course.
Now, don't let me keep you.
If you think she's the one,
we could have
Victor talk to her.
You do realize she is
literally my only friend.
I need the mayor.
I need proof.
But, sir, what if Ms.
Falcone, not to say it is her,
has seen to it that the
mayor is missing, well,
permanently?
I could be chasing a ghost
while she prepares her next move.
I wish I had a spy close
to her. Someone quiet.
Bring me Martin.
Who?
The boy with the
pad around his neck.
The one who can't talk.
I thought I was
clear. We're done.
Penguin suspects something.
What are you talking about?
He was just here saying that
he couldn't come to the party
I'm having tonight
for the orphanage.
He knows someone paid the
mayor to make you captain.
I think he suspects me.
- Have you warned the mayor?
- I'm not a fool, Jim.
I had him leave town
after your appointment.
Sounds like you have your
bases covered as usual.
Thanks for the heads
up about Penguin.
Don't call me again.
This is Harper.
Gordon, line one.
Says it's private.
Sofia.
Wrong. Try again.
You son of a bitch.
Attaboy, Jim.
Or should I say "Captain"?
Congratulations, by the way.
So, do you remember
when you said
the rot in Gotham
went from high to low?
You've hit the nail on the head.
Police were low,
and now it's time
for Gotham's elite
to feel the pain.
Enter phase two.
I won't spoil the reveal.
Hurry outside for a little taste
of what's to come.
Ciao, mon ami.
He's outside. Let's go.
GCPD.
Make way. GCPD.
- Back up. Back up.
- Excuse me.
Are they dead?
Get forensics here.
And I want this whole
area closed off. No press.
That pig's eating that guy.
Now, Harper.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
Where's breakfast?
Breakfast was produced and
consumed by yours truly at breakfast time.
It is now a fast approaching
luncheon, Master Bruce.
Whatever. Just give me a coffee.
Enjoying the benefits
of another night out on
the tiles with Tommy Elliot
and his band of
miscreants, are we?
How absolutely delightful.
I know what you're going
through, you know, Master Bruce.
Yeah?
I went out with my
friends. I'm hungover.
It doesn't take a
genius to figure it out.
You're lost is what you are.
I've seen that countless
times in young men.
Going off to war
with a clear purpose
only to return home to a
normal life, unable to assimilate,
confused, angry.
And they make a
complete tosh of it.
I don't really care.
You killed Ra's al Ghul.
Vengeance for
your parents' death
has been your driving
force for so long.
You are completely
lost without it.
I need to call Tommy.
Have you forgotten
what day it is today?
- Give me my phone.
- You have, ain't you?
Today is the day my
father took me camping.
We put a rock on
top of Mount Bristol.
We did it every year.
Now give me my phone.
You are Bruce Wayne,
son of Thomas Wayne.
And the sooner you start
remembering that, the better.
So, you drink your coffee,
you go upstairs, you put
your kit on 'cause you and I,
we're going for a walk.
According to the
medical examiner,
both victims had been
living outdoors for some time,
most likely homeless.
Now, see these incisions.
He removed their organs.
- Any idea why?
- Not yet.
The Pyg all but announced
that his next victims
would be the rich and powerful.
The high in Gotham.
So why is he killing
the homeless?
You are asking for
logic from a psychopath.
From him, yeah. Everything he's
done has been thought through carefully.
There was a card
on the table in French.
It said, "Long live
the revolution."
Maybe he's using them
to make a statement.
He wants the city's attention.
For what?
He said this is just a
taste of what's to come.
There's a piece
that's still missing.
The homeless are
densest in The Narrows
I'm gonna start there.
A hell of a first
day to be captain.
Yeah.
Call me if you
find anything else.
We checked all buildings in
the three-block radius, Captain.
Nothing.
All right. Widen it
out a couple of blocks.
Focus on buildings with
protected loading docks.
Captain, that was Lucius Fox.
Final tox came back.
Both victims had sodium sulfide
and chlorine residue on their skin.
He says it's common
in paper manufacturing.
There's an old paper
plant a few blocks from here
that closed down a while
back. Let's check that out.
Backup still incoming.
Should we wait?
No.
GORDON: Over here.
What is he doing to them?
Taking their organs.
HARPER: A smoker oven?
He's cooking them.
Harper.
Drop the gun, Captain.
Shoot this bastard.
Drop it!
Thank you.
You found me too soon, James.
The table is not yet set and
no meal should be served
before its time.
You want a hostage? Take me.
No, no, no, no, no.
That won't do at all.
You must see my final act.
Along with all of Gotham!
Right. Well, it's
a lovely day for it.
Best foot forward.
Very distinguished.
Sofia tells me you're taking part
in a performance this evening.
Well, she's quite
a lady, isn't she?
She's been a
friend to both of us.
Or has she?
Martin.
I worry Sofia is only
pretending to be my friend.
And worse,
I fear she may be using you.
Now.
I have been running
this over in my mind.
And there are two ways
this might have gone.
One, Sofia chose a
specific orphan, you,
to place in my path.
She groomed you,
she told you how to act.
Or,
Sofia simply collected
a group of children
hoping one would gain my trust,
and make me
easier to manipulate.
In this version,
you are innocent.
Martin.
This is the version I
very badly want to believe.
But I need proof
of our friendship.
I need to know if my
suspicions are correct.
And if so, what
Sofia is planning,
and who she is planning it with.
I need you to be my
eyes and my ears.
Do you think you could do that?
Don't let me down, Martin.
Please.
GORDON: I want a
city-wide BOLO on that van.
I want every cop in Gotham
on the streets looking for Harper.
She will not be the
Pyg's next victim.
- Go.
- All right.
- All right. Let's go.
- Let's go.
- Captain Gordon.
- Captain Gordon!
Captain Gordon! Captain Gordon!
Is it true that the serial killer
known as the Pyg is back?
That he's responsible for the scene
outside the GCPD this morning?
We believe so, yes.
We've also heard he's
kidnapped a GCPD detective.
How can you keep the
people of Gotham safe
when you can't protect
your own officers?
We remain hopeful for
Detective Harper's safe return.
Let me be clear.
The GCPD will stop this monster.
- That's a promise.
- And if you fail,
will you be pushed aside
like Harvey Bullock was?
We're done here. Thank you.
Captain Gordon!
What about the rumor that the
Pyg is now cooking his victims?
Who told you that?
Is it true?
As I said, the GCPD will
bring the Pyg to justice.
That's all.
Captain Gordon! Captain Gordon!
Someone leaked to the press
that the Pyg is cooking his victims.
Maybe it was the Pyg.
We know he wants attention.
Look, Jim.
Everyone in the
department is on your side.
Yeah.
There is something
you need to see.
"I grant this food will
be somewhat dear,
"and therefore very
proper for landlords who,
"as they have already
devoured most of the parents,
"seem to have the
best title to the children."
It's Jonathan Swift,
A Modest Proposal.
He made an argument for cannibalism
about the rich eating the poor.
The poor are the homeless.
But who are the rich?
Swift didn't just talk about
the rich eating the poor.
He specifically
mentioned the orphans.
I know where he's going.
He left this for me.
He's doing exactly what he did
with Harvey. It could be a trap.
And I won't lead more
officers to their deaths.
- You're going alone?
- I'm sorry, Lucius.
Where's Chef Louis?
Ici, mademoiselle.
It's such a pleasure
to meet you in person.
I was expecting you earlier.
Apologies. I was detained.
But I've made a small
change in the menu.
I've steered us away
from haute cuisine
to something a bit more mundane.
Voila.
I'm calling them
Gotham meat pies.
Your guests will die for them.
I've made us a delicious
brown English stew
with herb dumplings,
Master Bruce.
Your father used to
love it when I made stew.
Did I ever tell you how
I met your old man?
In London.
He was doing postgrad
work there. He told me.
Yeah, but no details.
Well, I was just out of
the army. Two months.
I don't remember any of it.
All a bit of blur, really.
Booze, drugs, brawling.
A sucking great black cloud.
One day I wake up
and I'm lying in this alley,
and I'm covered in blood.
Don't know how.
So, I picked myself up, I
took myself straight down
to the police station,
turn myself in,
hoping that they would
chuck me into the big house
and throw away the key.
And they told me to
shut up, sit down and wait.
And there was this really
annoying Yank wandering about,
dressed like he's ready
for a game of tennis,
and it was your dad.
Anyway, he bowls up to me
and asks me what I'd done.
Asking me questions.
Eventually, you know, I
found myself telling him
stuff that I was too
frightened even to think about.
But I guess it'd
just been building.
Anyway, at that point, the
desk sergeant called him over
and your dad turned
around at me, and he said,
"Alfred, last night, I was
being attacked in the alley.
"And you started
fighting this geezer.
"I headed on my
toes, and I ran away."
And I said, "Yeah, but that's not
what happened, is it, Thomas?"
And he says, "It is now."
Your father saved my life.
His friendship saved me.
You see, I know what
it's all like being lonely,
hoping that the
world will punish you.
I can help you.
- Bruce, listen to me...
- Alfred, I hear you.
I just don't want to
talk about this right now.
All right.
Well, this looks lovely.
The rocks are gone. They
must've fell out in the car.
The keys are in
the bag, just there.
(ENGINE STARTING)
- Beautiful.
- So nice to see you, dear.
- Thanks.
- Yes.
Oswald, you came!
Look at you two.
So handsome.
I know how important
tonight's party is to you.
And I wouldn't
have forgiven myself
if I had missed
Martin's performance.
Why don't you go
find the other children?
Did you locate the mayor?
Unfortunately, no.
But I've not given up hope.
Well, I, for one, am happy.
This way you get to
come to my dinner.
I need to go check on the
chef. He seems a bit odd.
Please, try and enjoy yourself.
Hello, Martin.
What are you writing?
Don't make a noise.
(SHUSHING)
I'm a cop. Who are you?
A waiter.
I'm looking for a man.
Caucasian, about five foot ten.
He would've brought
the food. Maybe the chef.
The chef's in the kitchen
Look, I just got hired tonight.
Whatever the dude's
into, I have no idea.
You're okay. You're okay.
Do me a favor. Find Ms.
Falcone, bring her to me.
- Can you do that for me?
- Yeah.
What's that in your jacket?
I don't...
Jim Gordon really is an
impressive policeman.
- Was he alone?
- It seems so.
But, man,
whatever it is you're into,
my partner and I,
our rates just doubled.
(HARPER MOANING)
Harper.
Hi, friends. The
Falcone orphanage
is the realization of a
long-cherished dream.
And one that would
have not been possible
without your support.
So, thank you.
- Cheers.
Now, if you could please take
your seats in the next room,
a few of the children
have prepared a song.
Where's Martin?
I wanted to wish him luck.
Ah. Off getting ready, no doubt.
Oswald, I've been thinking,
maybe things
happened for a reason.
Licensing crime was a bold move,
but it would've destroyed you.
Whoever had Jim
Gordon appointed captain,
may actually have saved you.
By attempting to destroy
everything I ever created?
- Oswald...
- Enough!
If you're going to
confess, confess.
And face the consequences.
- (GUNSHOTS)
- (SCREAMING)
So sorry to interrupt.
The servers are
getting everyone seated.
We don't want the
food to get cold.
Shall we go in to dinner?
Chop-chop.
All right.
I stopped the bleeding, I think.
That's the best I can do
until I can get you out of here.
I gotta get that door open.
- Gordon.
- Maybe I can get the hinges off.
Gordon.
Idiots forgot to search me.
Is this another
one of your plans?
No.
Ladies and gentlemen, as
you by now have surmised,
there's been a
change in the program.
Tonight we are proud to present
the six merry Gothamites
of Squatter's Row
and Martin from the
Falcone home and school
for orphans, in our rendition of
the meat pie tango.
(TANGO MUSIC PLAYING)
Bob.
Fricks.
Trish.
Nunuh.
Cyrano.
Vincent.
You have it coming
You only have yourself to blame
If you would've been fair
If you would've been keen
I bet you these pies
Wouldn't taste the same
Enough! Where are
the other children?
If you hurt them, I swear...
(ALL SCREAMING)
Rude, I'm not finished.
Sit down.
Pull it out, and the
next one's in her eye.
Oswald, no.
Don't.
Now, to answer your
question, my dear,
the other children and your staff
are safely locked in the kitchen.
Despite appearances,
I am not an animal.
Martin, may we continue?
You have all fed upon the
poor of Gotham for years.
Now, you're going to
know what they taste like.
Please open your envelopes
and look at the photographs inside.
Come on.
Open them!
Who is Trish?
Well, I thought you should
see who you are eating.
Bob, Fricks, Trish,
Nunuh, Cyrano, and Vincent
all deserve our gratitude.
So, these pies are...
People. Yup,
they're people pies.
People.
And you're all
going to eat them.
(ALL GROAN IN DISGUST)
Absolutely not.
Okay.
Let's try this again.
No!
Eat, or I kill the boy.
But he's just an orphan.
What did you say?
Well, these are made
of people, for God's sake.
You can't expect us, I mean...
So they kill some urchin.
What a waste of a good pie.
But I do applaud the sentiment.
Especially, as you, Mr. Cobblepot,
are the reason I'm here.
Me? Why?
I could've chosen any
gathering of wealthy Gothamites
who've gotten fat
upon the poor, but you,
with your Pax Penguina,
you are the biggest
glutton of them all.
You have gorged
yourself on this city's heart,
its lungs, its liver.
Why should today
be any different?
Now, eat, little penguin. Eat.
Eat the pies or the boy dies.
(RETCHING)
If you don't all eat,
I will hunt you
down and kill you all!
Now, that's what I like to see.
And as mother
always used to say,
"Nobody leaves until
every plate is clean."
It's a compliment to the
chef. And I love compliments.
And Ms. Falcone...
Mangia, signorina.
Only if you don't hurt him.
Can you help me?
Yes.
(GROANS)
No!
He'll kill the kid!
Get off of me!
Martin!
Jim!
Get out of here!
Go!
Come on, Jim.
Don't give up.
You will ruin everything.
Should be better.
How is your hand?
I'll be fine.
How's Martin?
He's stronger than he looks.
You paid off the mayor to
make Jim Gordon captain.
Yes.
And you want me to believe
that you did this out of friendship.
To save me.
I tried to talk you out
of the license program,
you wouldn't listen.
There seemed no other way.
Of course, it's equally
plausible that you are my enemy
intent upon my destruction.
You could choose
to see it that way.
The choice is yours, Oswald.
Well,
whatever your actual reasoning,
you went behind my back.
I would be justified
in killing you.
But what you were
going to do for Martin,
that was real.
Don't ever betray me again.
Never.
I will abandon the licenses.
But Jim Gordon
cannot be captain.
Pick someone else then.
Gordon's less
than nothing to me.
Oh, my God, look!
- It's the Pyg!
It's really him.
CROWD: Bye,
bye, piggy, bye, bye.
- REPORTER 1: Captain Gordon!
- REPORTER 2: Captain Gordon!
- Captain Gordon!
Is that the Pyg?
Did you really catch him?
The suspect known
as the Pyg is in custody.
Detective Vanessa Harper is
on her way to Gotham General
and is expected to
make a full recovery.
The GCPD kept its promise.
Captain Gordon.
Yes?
Thank you.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
Come on.
Hey, Alfred!
How was your walk?
Everybody out now.
Nobody move.
This is not your house.
If I want my friends
to stay, they're staying.
Like hell they are.
Dude, your butler
is a little out of line.
Have you been hitting
the sherry, Jeeves?
You have no idea what extreme
danger you are now in, son.
If I was you, I would walk away.
Yeah, whatever.
Meet us at the club.
Come on, driver will take us.
Well, you...
You certainly showed a
new side of yourself today
- haven't you, Master Bruce?
- Save it, Alfred.
You tell me a story
about you and my Dad, and
I'm supposed to get all weepy.
You don't know what
I'm going through.
You and I are nothing alike.
Then talk to me.
Let me know how I can help you.
You can't!
Like you said, I did what I did.
I killed Ra's.
I avenged my parents'
death, and guess what?
Nothing changed.
It made no difference.
So then what did I do it for?
How can you help that?
I can help with the
way that you're feeling.
But you need to talk to me.
You have to face up
to who you really are.
Stop telling me who I am.
I know who I am.
And if you really
want to help me,
you can stop trying to be my
father, and you can be my butler.
Clean this place up.
Tommy!
You're the hero of the day.
I was just doing my job.
I know you hate
me for what I did,
but you deserve to be captain.
I went to your father for help,
I knew what I was getting into.
It doesn't mean
I have to like it.
But you accept it.
Because I do deserve it.
Just like Gotham
deserves law and order.
And I'm gonna
make sure it gets it.
You don't think
I want that, too?
I'm not your enemy, Jim.
I never will be.
Did you find anything out?
"I saw Sofia
"kissing the policeman."
Is this true?
Martin, you are a good friend.
As for Sofia,
she will answer
for what she's done.
I swear.
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
English Template